<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Eutaxia tōu agroū: or A vindication of a regulated inclosure Wherein is plainly proved, that inclosure of commons in general and the inclosure of Catthorp in the county of Leicester in particular, are both lawful and laudable. As also that those evils which do too usually accompany inclosure of commons, are not the faults of inclosure, but of some inclosers only. By Joseph Lee minister of the Gospel.</title>
            <author>Lee, Joseph.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B25727</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828961</idno>
  <idno type="VID">207043</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264212016</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L843A</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828961</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99828961e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B25727)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 207043)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1971:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Eutaxia tōu agroū: or A vindication of a regulated inclosure Wherein is plainly proved, that inclosure of commons in general and the inclosure of Catthorp in the county of Leicester in particular, are both lawful and laudable. As also that those evils which do too usually accompany inclosure of commons, are not the faults of inclosure, but of some inclosers only. By Joseph Lee minister of the Gospel.</title>
                  <author>Lee, Joseph.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by E.C. and are to be sold by Thomas Williams at the Bible in Little-Britain,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first three words in the title are in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Goldsmiths' Library, University of London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Inclosures --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Catthorpe (England) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:207043:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:207043:1"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: OR A VINDICATION OF <hi>A Regulated Inclosure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein is plainly proved, that Inclosure of Commons in general and the Inclosure of <hi>Catthorp</hi> in the County of <hi>Leicester</hi> in particular, are both lawful and laudable.</p>
            <p>As also that those evils which do too usually accompany Inclosure of Commons, are not the faults of Inclosure, but of some Inclosers only.</p>
            <p>By JOSEPH LEE Minister of the Gospel.</p>
            <q>
               <p>And herein do I exercise my self, to have alwaies a conscience void of offence toward God and toward man, <bibl>
                     <hi>Act. 24.16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>But sanctifie the Lord God in your heart, and be ready alwaies to give an answer to every man that asketh you a reason of the hope that is in you with meeknesse and fear; Having a good conscience, that whereas they speak evil of you, as of evil doers, they may be ashamed that falsly accuse your good conversation in Christ, <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Pet. 3.15, 16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>Si sufficiat accusare, quis innocens erit?</l>
               <l>Allegatio sine probatione calumnia.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>E.C.</hi> and are to be sold by <hi>Thomas Williams</hi> at the Bible in <hi>Little-Britain,</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:207043:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:207043:2"/>
            <head>The Epistle to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Christian and courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may be thou mayest wonder, that I a Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ist<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r of the Gospel should meddle with a businesse of this nature: The truth is, I wonder more at my self, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very conscious of my little experience in the things of this world: This subject is not plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing unto me, but necessity commands, and I obey. I have been charged to act against con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science in giving my consent to this Inclosure, I have been challenged to preach in publick, what I have privately professed to be my judgement; but judge it not convenient to answer this cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lenge, for these Reasons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. When I come into the pulpit, I come upon my Masters businesse, not my own.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I am very sensible that if our pulpits had soun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded more of the things of Christ, and lesse of the things of the world, it had been better with us then it is this day.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb facs="tcp:207043:3"/>3. What falleth from the mouth is oft perverted, misconstrued and falsly reported, but <hi>litera scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta manet,</hi> what I write thou maist judge of; I choose therefore this way, to let thee know that I have not sinned against conscience, I have done nothing in this businesse conscience doubting, much lesse opposing, and I hope not erring. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, is a double knowledge, and hath a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aspect, it looks backward and forward; back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards upon Gods will revealed, forwards upon our own actions performed; I blesse God I have compared both these, and examined this businesse in that highest Court on earth, and I finde my self cleared in that the Judge doth not condemn the fact. True I know I have sinned in this action, as I have in all my best duties and most fervent prayers; if the Lord should be extreme to mark what I have done amisse in my holy things, I am not ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to answer him one word for a thousand sins; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to the action it self, I finde Gods waies and my will to meet, and no contradiction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Gods precepts and my actions; God having no where prohibited, what I have herein practised; seeing therefore my heart condemns me not,<note place="margin">Joh. 3 21.</note> I have confidence towards God, and consequently solid consolation, against all the uncharitable surmises, opprobrious imputations and false accusations of men: I passe very little to be judged by thee or mans judgement, he that judgeth is the Lord: yea although some of Gods own should have hard and harsh thoughts of me, yet God will not condemn me:
<pb facs="tcp:207043:3"/> Conscience is Gods Court of Chancery, and that relief I meet with in that high Court of equity,<note place="margin">Prov. 15.15.</note> is to me a continual feast; God I am sure will not condemn, whom a good conscience rightly infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med doth acquit: I say rightly informed, perhaps some will say, that is <hi>petitio principii,</hi> a taking that for granted, which is not proved. Truly I have neglected no means of information, considering as well what was said against it, as what was said for it: neither did I do it suddenly, but upon mature deliberation, and upon result, I am now very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, that the lawfulnesse and laudability of the inclosure by us practised, is in these papers fully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed; but I may not be Judge in mine own cause, I leave them therefore to thy candid censure: First I pray consider what I have said, and then judge without prejudice and partiality: and the Lord give thee, and me also, understanding in this, and in all things, which is the earnest prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Cotesbatch,</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Nov.</hi> 12.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Thy friend, <hi>Joseph Lee.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="epitaph">
            <lg>
               <l>—<hi>Si quid novisti rectius istis,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Candidus imperti; si non, his utere mecum.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If ought thou knowest better to be,</l>
               <l>Impart it; else use these with me,</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:207043:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:207043:4"/>
            <head>A VINDICATION OF A Regulated Inclosure.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ruth is the daughter of Time, and Time the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of Truth: all is not gold that glistereth, nor all truth that seems so; Truth it self may be sometimes clouded and unknown to many lovers of it; a glazed piece may passe a while for currant coyn, when good money a little blurred is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused, but time and truth will bring it to the touchstone: a gilded error may seem a glorious truth, but time and truth will manifest it to be at best a flourishing falshood. A pretended error is sometimes truth concealed; unmask it, and it proveth truth revealed. All things are not sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full which are so esteemed; as there are sins reall, so there are sins imaginary; as there are sins of Gods making which his Law hath forbidden, so there are sins of the Devils making: the god of this world hath so blinded the eyes of the Idolater, that he judgeth it to be his sin not to bow to an Idol; and the Heretick, that he judgeth it to be his sin not to oppose the Gospel. And there are sins also of mens making, which mans brain doth fancy to be
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:207043:5"/> sins, although God hath not prohibited them: beleeve it Christians, if we be truly sensible of those great and God provoking crimes, and daly deviations from the will of God, which we rush upon as the horse rusheth into the battel; we have little need to adde unto our burden, by charging our selves with sins which God hath not made sins, and imputing sins to our selves which God doth not impute unto us: that God which hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned wil-worship and self-devised service, <hi>who hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired this at your hands?</hi> Isa. 1.12. doth not approve that we should condemn our selves for self-devised sins. It hath passed for an undeniable maxime amongst some, that all inclosure of Commons is sinful; but time and truth hath now discovered, that inclosure in it self is no way vitious, but necessary at least for the well being of the Common-wealth. The proof of this is the task I have undertaken, <hi>viz</hi> That some Inclosure cannot justly be charged with sin: if you call for example for the better assurance, I present you here with one, wherein I am most concerned, <hi>viz.</hi> the intended Inclosure of <hi>Catthorp</hi> in the County of <hi>Leicester:</hi> That which I have to say herein, I shall reduce to two heads, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Inclosure of <hi>Catthorp</hi> is,
<list>
                  <item>1. Lawfull.</item>
                  <item>2. Laudable.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And consequently not sinfull.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <p n="1">1. That the Inclosure of <hi>Catthorp</hi> is lawful, appeareth because it doth no injury to any: that it doth no injury appeareth, because it is profitable to all concerned therein: Now there are four sorts of men besides our selves to be considered, 1. The Minister. 2. The Poor. 3. The Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages. 4. The Tenants.</p>
               <p>That it is profitable to our selves, I think few will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; else what mean those outcries against us, that filthy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere is our end; or if it be not, <hi>volenti non fit injuria,</hi> we are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>illing to suffer that wrong.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:207043:5"/>
               <p>That it is profitable to all others concerned as well as our selves, appeareth by considering them apart.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is profitable to the Minister; because his living, never worth above 60 <hi>l. per annum,</hi> and sometimes in bad years but 40. or 50 <hi>l.</hi> will be made worth 80 <hi>l. per annum,</hi> we having covenanted constantly to pay unto him and his successors for ever, in lieu of his tithes about 54 <hi>l. per annum,</hi> the Gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>be at 15 <hi>s.</hi> by the acre will make up the rest; besides he himself hath consented to it, and therefore it probable would not injure himself.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The poor, now having no part of the Fields nor Commons belonging to their houses, will hereby gain 14. acres of Land, which we have freely given unto them to be setled upon Feoffees in trust for the use of the poor of <hi>Catthorp</hi> for ever, by the same Law that our own Lands are setled upon our selves, so that none can ever de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive them of it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It will be advantagious to the Cottagers whose Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons being now worth <hi>communibus annis,</hi> but 8. or 9 <hi>s. per annum,</hi> will be made worth 35 <hi>s. per annum</hi> at the least.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The advantage of the Tenants I confesse will be according to the dealing of the Landlord with them; That we will not deal kindly with them, none have reason to prejudge; or if any of us should rack our Rents in inclosure, it is not the fault of the inclosure, but the inclosers, and that not as inclosers, but as unmercifull Landlords: have we not the same power to do the like in common fields, if the Lord do not give us more mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful hearts? I hope we shall stop the mouthes of all gainsayers in this particular. Sure I am they will be great gainers, although they should pay a double Rent, if that be true, which the Petitioners to the Parliament against Inclosure did affirm, <hi>viz.</hi> That men by Inclosure do make a treble advantage of their Lands, absurdly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging that as an argument against it, which in sound judgement is a good argument for it.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:207043:6"/>
               <p>Object. <hi>The allowance to the Poor will not be sufficient for their maintenance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> We are bound by the Law to provide for the impotent poor (if this be not sufficient) as much as in common fields, the Law injoyns us to provide for their being, this we adde in charity for their better being; except the ancient Cottages which have land laid out in lieu of their Commons, there are only four ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Cottages in the Town, and for present there are not above twelve persons, men, women and children, that do, or at least can pretend to poverty: the 14. Acres given to the poor, will be worth in time 14 <hi>l. per annum,</hi> which will amount to five pence by the week to every poor inhabitant, which will be a good help to them: sure I am, young people are very eager to marry into our Town, being incouraged by that large provision we have made for the poor.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>It will wrong the Poor, because they will want work when the Town is Inclosed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> Except two or three old men, who are unable to work, whose sons are Tradesmen, as also the rest of the Cottages, there are only three day-labourers in the Town; Is it probable that the cutting of hedges, thresh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of corn, and keeping of grounds as shepherds, should not finde them as much work as they had before? <hi>Credat Judaeus Apella, non ego.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> 2. Many poor are maintained in working about Wool and Cloth in this Nation, especially in those parts which are generally inclosed, and these kept in constant work; whereas in the common fields divers poor men in the winter have not three daies work in the week to maintain their family: I have heard a godly man an experimentall Clothier affirm, that if there was an effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual course taken, that no Wool might be transported beyond sea, no poor man or woman in <hi>England,</hi> that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>illing to work, could lack work.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> 3. Have not the Lawes of the Land sufficiently
<pb facs="tcp:207043:6"/> provided, that none shall want work? if any in <hi>Catthorp</hi> should want work, may they not be relieved upon their own complaint to the next Justice of Peace? To what end were the Laws made if not to be executed?</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>It will depopulate, Inclosure being usually attended with plucking down of houses, and destroying of Towns.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> As there are many depopulations in Inclosure, so there are many Inclosures without depopulation, as in particular, <hi>Market Bosworth, Coten, Carlton, Shenton,</hi> all in one parish: <hi>Nelson, Cadsby, Ʋpton, Bilson, Stapleton, Twi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cross, Barton, Higham, Stoke, Golding,</hi> which Towns are all near together: the like may be said of <hi>Little Glenn, Croft, Ashby Magna, Cosford, Woscot,</hi> and divers others; in which places although they have been inclosed some twenty, some thirty, some forty, or fifty years; there is neither depopulation nor decay of houses: if some Inclosers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>populate, these things are <hi>vitia personarum non rei,</hi> the faults of the persons, not the thing; the offences of some Inclosers, not inclosure. Are depopulation and inclosure inseparable companions? no, this a meer <hi>non sequitur,</hi> it followeth not: as if a man should say, because many are drunk in an Inne, therefore there ought to be no Inne to entertain travellers: And this I am the more confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in, because they that preach and write and talk most against Inclosure, bring not an argument aganst Inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure as inclosure, but against depopulating inclosures, such and such inclosures, which to me is an evidence that they are convinced in their consciences, that some Inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures are lawful.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> 2. When Inclosure doth produce depopulation, it is only in such Towns as are in the hands of one or few men, and not in such Towns where there are severall freeholders of small Tenements, as it is with us at <hi>Catthorp;</hi> our whole continent being but about five hundred and eighty acres, is now in the hands of eight Free-holders, and five or six ancient Cottages, who are also Free-holders.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:207043:7"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> 3. We have covenanted so far as we can by Law to uphold all our ancient Tenements and Cottages to be continued habitations, and a competent quantity of Land to be used with each of them.</p>
               <p>Reply. <hi>But Covenants will not binde posterity, they may depopu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, although you do not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> We have done our utmost to binde posterity and successors; if our acts will not binde them, the defect is not in us, but in the Lawes of the Land.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> 2. If after ages should depopulate, the fault is not ours, who have declared our dislike of it and done our utmost to prevent it, but theirs who shall be the actors in such devastations, it being already clearly demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strated, that depopulation doth not necessarily follow inclosure.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> 3. After ages might destroy their habitations in Common-fields, although it had not been inclosed, and this all will grant would not be our fault. Mr. <hi>Caldecot</hi> (who is only in a capacity to depopulate, because he alone hath more Tenements than one) if he was of that minde, might pluck down his two Tenements, which he now setteth to Tenants, and lay his Land to his own house and plow it himself with two good Teams as it lyeth in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: so that he might depopulate although he should not inclose: our Inclosure then will prevent depopulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, at least for this time rather then occasion it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> 4. It was well observed by the Author of the Answer to Mr. <hi>Moores</hi> Sermon, that such depopulations as accompany Inclosure are usually made at first, and not in succeeding generations: I know a Town which was depopulated upon the first inclosure about fifty years since; but since the first depopulation, not one house de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed, but divers houses increased.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>You will keep fewer servants, and so depopulate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> As many maid-servants will be employed as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, there are but about ten men-servants and shepherds employed by all the Farmers and Husbandmen in the
<pb facs="tcp:207043:7"/> Town as it lyeth in Commons, and there will be six or seven kept in Inclosure. It's confessed, that it's probable three or four shepherd-boyes will be necessitated to lay aside that idle imployment: which in very many places proves destructive, specially to the souls of those Lads; in that, poor creatures, they are brought up by this means, without either civill or religious education, when on the work-daies they should be at school, and on the Lords day at Church, to learn the waies of God, they are play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at nine holes under a bush, in the interim their cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell make a prey on their neighbors corn, and they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves are made a prey to Satan, being so rooted and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veted into sin being young, that many times they live and die in a total ignorance of God and Gospel: now if upon the Inclosure such boyes as these, be set to trades and such like imployments, wherein they may more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently frequent Gods Ordinances, and come to the saving knowledge of Christ, will any call this depopu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> 2. Let it be granted that our land and businesse ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nearer together fewer servants will be kept; are any bound to keep more servants then are needful for their businesse; or may they not cast how to do the same bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinesse with least labour: <hi>Frustra fit per plura quod fieri potest per pauciora,</hi> In vain that is done by more, which may be done by lesse: Is a man bound to keep servants to pill strawes or labour in vain? by what Law? if this prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple be good, that all are bound so to carry on their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs in the world, as to imploy servants, although to their own disadvantage; I dare say, the much applauded plough must be cast into the ditch, and much admired ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufacture of tillage must be exchanged for digging with spades and mattocks, which would imploy more men than tillage.</p>
               <p>Reply. <hi>To that maxime, In vain &amp; e. an ingenuous friend in discourse returned this reply, that it holds in naturals, not in poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:207043:8"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> 1. I confesse it may be good policy in such Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-weals, where are such a multitude of people, that they cannot otherwise be imployed, to keep them in work, about that which is of little profit, rather then they should be idle. But blessed be God, our people may be imployed in the working of wooll, flax, hemp, woad, and other commodities, which are very beneficial to the Common-wealth, and therefore they need not labour in vain.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> 2. There is with us rather a scarcity than a su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluity of servants, their wages being advanced to such an extraordinary height, that they are like ere long to be masters, and their masters servants, many poor husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men being forced to pay near as much to their servants for wages as to their Landlords for Rent.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>It will decay tillage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> 1. This is indeed the most probable argument against Inclosure, and that which I confesse hath put formerly some scruple upon my self, till I was fully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced by experience that it hath no weight in it, if considered in the ballance of judgement: look upon all the Inclosures within three miles round about <hi>Catthorp, Bigging, Browns-Over, Coten, Cosford, Shawell, Hall field, Street<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field, Sister, Over, Moore-barn, Cotesbatch, Cotes, Pultney, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterton, Starmer,</hi> and the most of these Inclosures have been plowed within thirty years, and the rest are now about to be plowed; and what great quantity of corn hath been gained in them, no man in the Countrey that hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served them can be ignorant, some or other of these being never without great store of corn.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> 2. What is it that makes corn so cheap as it is this day, but the breaking up of old Inclosures. I deny not but the Lord of his mercy hath crowned the earth with more then ordinary plenty in the common fields, but this alone could not make corn so cheap as it hath been these late years: that the plenty of corn makes it cheap, I think it is undeniable, and then it will follow, that there
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:207043:8"/> is a double quantity of corn now in the land, compared with that which hath been formerly; because the price of corn hath been commonly double, and sometimes tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: but few common fields have now a double quantity of corn to that which they have had formerly. I have conferred with divers Ministers, which receive Tithes in kind, who do affirm the premises upon their certain knowledge to be true, and then it will follow, that the late plenty and double quantity of corn is got in new broken up inclosed grounds, whereof there are now very many in all places.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> 3. By what Law of God or man is every man bound to plow his land at all times, whether there be need of corn or no, although he can make more advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to himself by pasture? May not every one lawfully put his commodity to the best advantage, provided he do it without prejudice to others? do not all tradesmen cast to lay out their money upon such wares, as will be most advantagious to themselves? Have not Land-holders as much reason, and may they not with as good consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence put their lands to the best advantage? but many will lay heavie burdens upon others which themselves will not touch with one of their fingers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> 4. Whensoever there is the least want of corn, and mens Land is fit to bear corn, men will plow up their inclosed land for their own profit; it's an undeniable maxime, That every one by the light of nature and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son will do that which makes for his greatest advantage, but whensoever corn beareth a considerable rate, <hi>viz.</hi> wheat four or five shillings, and barly two shillings six pence, men may make more profit, by plowing then pasture; and consequently will plow for their own advantage: why else do men usually give 40 <hi>s.</hi> an acre for tillage, when no man can afford to give above 20 <hi>s.</hi> for the grazing of the same land?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> 5. Let it be granted, as it is not proved, that it is a duty incumbent upon all Land-holders at all times to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:207043:9"/> keep part of their land in tillage: this equally bindes all, as well in old as new Inclosures and common fields. I wish that those that so zealously impose this law upon others would first practise it themselves: suppose <hi>A. B.</hi> having 50 acres in <hi>C.</hi> is bound to plough such a quantity of it: the <hi>C. D.</hi> having land in <hi>B.</hi> is bound by the same law to plow as many acres proportionate to his land.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ans.</hi> 6. If judicious men shall find experimentally, that the Common-wealth will suffer for want of corn, if every man be left at liberty to plow or not to plow, why may it not be inacted by a law, that every Land-holder, as well in inclosures as common fields shall be forced to plow such a quantity of land as shall be thought conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient: this I am sure, would be more equal, then that all the toyle of tillage should be laid upon the common fields, (till their lands by continual plowing of more land then they are able to manure, are worn quite out of heart and made unfit for any thing as it is in many places) and in the interim the Inclosures go free.</p>
               <p>Object. Prov. 11.26. <hi>He that witholdeth corn, the people will curse him (or</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Hebr.</note>
                  <hi>smite him through) but blessing shall be upon the head of him that selleth it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> Two things in this Scripture to be considered, 1. What to withhold corn. 2. What to curse.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To withhold corn, is through a base avarice and greedinesse of gain, to hoard corn by thrusting it up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the barns and garners, and refusing to sell it to the poor in times of greatest want, still expecting that it will be dearer; withholding is then opposed to selling, and concerneth not those that have none to sell in hard times, this being a misery rather then a sin: neither is withhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding corn a sin at all times, but only in times of scarci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in times of plenty it is rather a vertue, there being no better friends to the Common-wealth, then such who having ability and conveniency, do in times of plenty reserve their corn for future times of poverty: Had not <hi>Josephs</hi> prudence provided granaries in the seven prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:207043:9"/> years of fulnesse, to supply the seven subsequent years of famine, all <hi>Egypt</hi> had perished, Gen. 41. yea all Israel, Gen. 42.1, 2. Hence it is provided by the statute Lawes of this land, that corn may be ingrossed and kept in granaries when it is of small price, <hi>Anno. Edw.</hi> 6. <hi>stat.</hi> 14. <hi>Anno</hi> 13. <hi>Elizab. stat.</hi> 25.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To Curse, is to wish evill from God to our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour: this is a thing utterly unlawful, God having commanded us to blesse, and prohibited cursing, Rom. 12.14, 15. Hereby men would make God an executioner to their base lusts: God must come down from heaven in all hast to revenge their quarrels, and serve their malicious hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours. True, we read in sacred writ, of some of Gods ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants which have cursed Gods enemies, Psa. 69.22, &amp;c. 2 Kin. 2.24. but these were not passionate maledictions, but Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetical predictions of Gods judgement, not so much in their own cause as Gods cause, incited by God, not their own lusts; and against such only whom they know to be Gods implacable enemies, Psal. 109.15, 17. compared; and therefore, although not to be rejected, yet not to be imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: This Scripture therefore is no encouragement to the people to curse even those that do sinfully withhold corn, but is rather an aggravation of the sin of such withholders, in that they do irritate and provoke the people to sin against God by cursing them. Whether God will second the sinful curses of men, although they curse such as are sinful, is a question to be considered: yet I acknowledge it is the just reward of those that walk irregularly, to be paid in their own coyn, and irregularly punished by the reproaches, execrations, and detestations of the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, Prov. 24.24. I say just from the hand of God, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though sinful in man: but what makes this against us? you will say it holds in analogy, against such as withhold their lands from plowing.</p>
               <p>Reply, 1. <hi>But what makes this against Inclosure as Inclosure, seeing many inclosures abound with corn.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:207043:10"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply,</hi> 2. It is granted that such as having land fit to plow in time of want, do withhold their lands from plowing, are equally guilty, as those that withhold their corn from selling, especially if they do it upon that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous consideration that corn will be dearer, when it is extraordinary dear already: If any Inclosers do so, let them answer for themselves; but as withholding of corn is not unlawful at all times, but expedient at some times, as in <hi>Josephs</hi> case, so if some men in times of plenty do rese<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve their land for times of penury, that they may then plow, such are not only provident husbands for themselves, but profitable members of the republick. That we in <hi>Catthorp</hi> will not plow when the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lth hath need of Corn, none have reason to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judge: if therefore any be so wicked and malicious (as I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ear and hear some there be) to curse us without cause, I hope we shall not render railing for railing, but shall,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Pray for them in our Saviours words, (Oh that we could do it with our Saviours Spirit!) <hi>Father forgive them, for they know not what they do,</hi> Luk. 23.34.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Pray for our selves, <hi>that we may be delivered from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonable men,</hi> 2 Thess. 3.2.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Comfort our selves in that promise of God, that <hi>the curse causlesse shall not come,</hi> Prov. 26.2.</p>
               <p>But let those bitter bloudy spirits, and cruel cursers look to it themselves, curses being like arrowes shot up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, that fall upon mens own heads; <hi>they that do</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laams <hi>work may expect to receive</hi> Baalams <hi>wages.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Object. <hi>There are many excellent promises made to tillage above other callings,</hi> Prov. 28.19. <hi>He that t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lleth his land shall have plenty of bread.</hi> Prov. 12.11. <hi>He that tilleth his land shall be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with bread.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> These promises are made to diligence in that calling, not to tillage as tillage; it's not the minde of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> so to omnifie tillage as to vilifie diligence in other callings, these promises are in the proportion of faith in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements to dilig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce in other callings; as appeareth
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:207043:10"/> by what followeth, Prov. 28.19. <hi>He that followeth the idle shall be filled with poverty.</hi> And Prov. 12.11. <hi>He that follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the idle, is destitute of understanding.</hi> Whatsoever are mens stations or vocations, God rewardeth the diligent, Prov. 10.4. <hi>The hand of the diligent maketh rich, but the slothful hand maketh poor.</hi> Prov. 13.14. <hi>The sluggard lusteth but his soul hath nought, but the soul of the diligent shall be made fat.</hi> As slothfulnesse in all callings doth clothe men with rags, Prov. 23.21. So the slothful plowman shall want bread, Prov. 20.4. <hi>The slothfull will not plow because of the winter, and therefore he shall beg in the summer and have nothing.</hi> If a shepherd be laborious in his calling, God will reward him as well as the painful plowman: the sacrifice of <hi>Abel</hi> a keeper of sheep was accepted, when the sacrifice of <hi>Cain,</hi> a tiller of the earth, was rejected. <hi>Jacob</hi> was faithfull in keeping <hi>Labans</hi> sheep, and God rewarded him, Gen. 30.42, 43. Yea <hi>Jacob</hi> brought up his children in that calling, Gen. 37.2. A keeper of sheep was an abomination to the Egyptians, Gen. 46.34. but the trade of the Israelites.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>Wo be to them which joyn house to house, and field to field, till there be no place, that they may be placed alone in the midst of the earth,</hi> Isa. 5.8.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> The Prophet reproveth the blinde ambition, and insatiable avarice of those that are not contented with their own large possessions, but <hi>per fas aut nefas, vi &amp; fraude,</hi> by right or wrong, force and fraud, without consideration of their poor neighbour, do grasp all into their own fists; neither, as <hi>Calvin</hi> notes upon the place,<note place="margin">Nec enim per se damnari po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test si quis agrum agro &amp; domum domui conjungat, sed animum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spexit propheta, qui satiari nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo modo potest, ubi semel haben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di cupiditate accenditur, <hi>Calv. in Loc.</hi>
                  </note> is the joyning of house to house and field to field simply condemned, but the greedy desire of it: a man whose family increaseth, if the next house be empty, may joyn it to his own; and a man whose stock of cattell increaseth, if the owner and possessor will willingly part with the next field, may lawfully joyn it to his own: but that which is justly condemned is such a joyning house to house and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:207043:11"/> field to field, which is joyned with oppression and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury to others; till there be no place which is not their own, and none left to their poor neighbour; nothing contenteth, but that they alone possesse the earth: this being the true meaning of the place, I grant that this taxeth those cruel inclosers and caterpillars of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, as reverend Mr. <hi>Dod</hi> calleth them, which set themselves to unpeople the Land, by destroying Towns, and turning out the poor: Let them answer for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, God will call such to an account: For my part I am so far from approving or practising such sinfull In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>closure, that I heartily wish that all the owners of such inclosures might be forced by a law, to repeople such places, rebuild their houses, and none might be suffered to rent such Land, but such as inhabit those decayed Towns; but this is the fault of the Inclosers, not the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>closure, <hi>vitium personae non rei.</hi> What makes this against in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>closure in general, or the Inclosure of <hi>Catthorp</hi> in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar? whose houses have we destroyed? whose Land have we invaded? every man shall enjoy the same quantity o land, which he did before; we have not taken away our neighbours land by force or fraud, but have by a general consent of the Land-holders, exchanged one acre of Land for another, for our conveniency: we have not taken away the Lands of the poor and laid them to our own, but have lessened our own Lands, and given part of them to the poor for ever.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>But God hath pursued Inclosure with his severe judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon the Inclosers and their posterity: we may read their doom wrote in text letters, and legible characters of misery, in that the Inclosers do seldome keep their Lands three generations: and here again is alledged,</hi> Isa. 5.8, 9. <hi>This is in mine ears, saith the Lord of host, surely many houses shall be desolate, even great and fair, without inhabitant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> 1. That cannot be looked upon as a judgement against Inclosers, which is common to other Land-holders which never did inclose: few in common fields do keep
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:207043:11"/> their Lands three generations, take <hi>Catthorp</hi> it self for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance: Mr. <hi>Caldecotts</hi> Land within the memory of some living, was sold by Mr. <hi>Leigh</hi> to Mr. <hi>Britton,</hi> and by Mr. <hi>Britton</hi> to Mr. <hi>Caldecot:</hi> Mr. <hi>Wildes</hi> Land within the same time hath been sold by Mr. <hi>Feilden</hi> to Mr. <hi>Elkinton,</hi> whose heirs sold it to Mr. <hi>Wilde:</hi> my own Land within 40 or 50 years, hath been sold by <hi>Pywell</hi> to <hi>Stanton,</hi> by <hi>Stanton</hi> to <hi>Joseph Smyth,</hi> whose Son in law sold it to my Father. <hi>Thomas Bronnes</hi> Land within a little more then twenty years, hath been sold by <hi>Charles Kilpacke</hi> to <hi>James Staples,</hi> who sold it to <hi>Henry Be</hi> father of the foresaid <hi>Thomas. Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Ernesby</hi>'s Land was sold by Mr. <hi>Feilding</hi> to Mr. <hi>Elkinton,</hi> whose Heir sold it to <hi>Thomas Wood,</hi> father in law to the said <hi>William.</hi> Only <hi>Edward Smiths</hi> Land hath continued in that family three generations.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> 2. Sometimes inclosers keep their Land many generations, <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es, Mysterton,</hi> and <hi>Pultney,</hi> have been in the hands of the <hi>Pultneys,</hi> and <hi>Starmar</hi> in the hands of the <hi>Caves</hi> many hundred year, two presidents that cannot be paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leld in the common fields.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> 3. Concerning those mentioned by the Prophet <hi>Isaiah,</hi> whose avarice and ambition is content with no mediocrity (who are like to <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, who hearing the Philosopher disputing that there was many worlds, is said to weep because he had not conquered one) I say when men let loose the reins to such unruly lusts, being never satisfied till their covetous hands have taken hold on other mens portions, God justly may, and many times doth blast their blessings, and curse their mercies, Mal. 2.2. plague their posterity and leave their houses without inhabitants: but what is this against our Inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure? that doth only improve our own mercies to the best advantage to our selves and the Common-wealth, without the least injury to others: I blesse God we are not partakers of such mens sins, and therefore hope we shall not be partners of their plagues.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:207043:12"/>
               <p>Object. Prov. 22.28. <hi>Remove not the ancient Land-mark which thy fathers have set, from whence some infer, that it is not lawful to exchange our fathers Lands for other Land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> The removing the Land-mark there prohibited, is when men by force or fraud remove the Land-mark of their poor neighbours whose Land is adjacent, and so take hold on part of their Land as their own, without consent, or giving any other Land in exchange; a sinful practise, too common in the common fields, where men make nothing to pull up their neighbours Land-mark to plow up their Land, and mow their Grasse that lyeth next them: This is the intent of the Holy Ghost, if we will give God leave to be his own interpreter. Prov. 23.20. <hi>Remove not the old Land-mark, and enter not into the field of the fatherlesse.</hi> So Deut. 19.14. <hi>Thou shalt not remove thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours Land-mark which they of old time have set.</hi> This sin brings a curse upon the actors and authors of it, Deut. 27.17. But this maketh nothing against a mutuall agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to exchange one Land for another, whereby both parties are advanced and neither injured; this being a set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Land-marks, not a removing them: we do not remove Land-marks to oppresse one another, but set Land-marks to keep each other from oppression: we doubt not but our Inclosure will prevent many such oppressions expressed in the premisses.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>Inclosure destroyeth horses which should serve the State in War.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> Few horses kept in common fields fit for service, one well kept will be more serviceable to the State then three that are jaded and tyred: besides, moneys are the sinews of war, if that be not wanting, the State cannot want either horses or men: but the sum of money that is payed in all taxes out of Inclosures is double to that which is payed out of the common fields of the same quantity.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>All have not consented, one that hath seven sheeps Commons doth withstand it, may you lawfully force him so part with
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:207043:12"/> his right of Common and accept of your allowance in stead thereof against his will? may you make a hedge in the Common without his consent? doth not the Prophet</hi> Micah <hi>pronounce a woe against such dealing as this?</hi> Mic. 2.2. Woe unto them that covet fields and take them by violence, and houses and take them away, so they oppresse a man in his house, a man in his heritage: <hi>what although you allow h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m a proportion of land of more value then his Commons are worth? Is not this</hi> Naboths <hi>case, do ye not act</hi> Ahabs <hi>part to the life?</hi> 1 King 21.2. Ahab <hi>offered money, or a better vineyard, yet</hi> Naboth <hi>refusing,</hi> Ahab <hi>is condemned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> 1. We do not force him to part with his right, he hath no land which he can mark for his own only right of Common: and we have right of Common as well as he: we do only divide our Common from his, and leave him a large proportion, himself and friends have confessed that it will be no personal wrong to him, the Land allotted him being four times as good as his Commons. We do not oppresse him in his heritage: I think if that woe pronounced by <hi>Micah</hi> was well consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, it might rather be retorted in that he doth threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by violence to pluck down our hedges, and force us to lay aside the improvement of our heritages, when our doing of it is confessed to be no wrong to him, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved no injury to others.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> 2. The case of <hi>Naboths</hi> Vineyard is far different from ours, it was unlawful for <hi>Naboth</hi> to exchange his vineyard with <hi>Ahab</hi> although for a better, because God had prohibited the I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raelites to sell their Land from their own Tribe: the reason rendred, Levit. 25.25. <hi>Because it was Gods:</hi> in case of poverty it might be morgaged, but not sold, the next kinsman must redeem it, vers. 25. and although it was never redeemed, yet in the year of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile it must be restored, vers. 26. Therefore the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Zelophehad</hi> must marry to husbands of their own tribe, because the inheritance of the children of Israel might not remove from tribe to tribe: <hi>Naboth</hi> was not
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:207043:13"/> of the same tribe with <hi>Ahab:</hi> had <hi>Naboth</hi> denied <hi>Ahab</hi> such a small courtesie only upon his own will, he had been a very unkinde subject; but his deni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l was groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon Gods will: besides, we desire nothing to be exchanged with him, but our own to be divided from his.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> 3. If he refuse to have his part of the Common sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from ours, and resolve to put himself to that trouble and charge, he may still intercommon amongst us, and put his seven sheep in any place, where he had right of Common before: our division of our own Common from each other, will be no impediment to him to use his Commons as before the Inclosure, the Land allotted to him, will fully content any of us whose Land he shall make choise of.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> 4. In that it's said we make our hedges upon his Common, we have three hundred parts for his one, and consequently set hedges upon our own part of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, not upon his. Surely there will be grasse enough for seven sheep notwithstanding the hedges in some of our grounds.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>You have taken away the Church Land, and given it to the poor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> We acknowledge that those small parcels of Land called Church-hadland and Church-layes (which were set apart by common consent, not any particular mans donation, for repair of the Church, or whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver other publick use the Town appoints) are part of that Land given to the poor; they being our own, why may not we dispose of them to what publique use we please? they were never worth above 20 <hi>s. per annum, communibus annis,</hi> which money did formerly bear the charges of the rich, and is now disposed of for the use of the poor: Is it unlawful to give it from our selves to others that have more need? Moreover the latter math of Mr. <hi>Elkintons</hi> piece, a thing of greater value is to be imployed to the same publick use as those Lands formerly.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:207043:13"/>
               <p>Object. <hi>Filthy lucre the end of your Inclosure, in that you aime at your own gain and not at Gods glory: It is also alledged that my s lf and other Ministers have preached, that mens actions are sinful, although not materially evil, if the ends be not Gods glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> Upon what ground it's said filthy lucre is our end I know not, unlesse all gain be filthy: true, such gain which is either gotten by indirect means, or prosecuted with covetous desires, the Scripture calleth <hi>filthy lucre,</hi> 1 Tim. 3.3. Tit. 1.11. 1 Pet. 5.2. till one of these be proved against us, what some affirm to be filthy lucre, I shall be bold to call honest advantage.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> 2. It's granted that those actions which are in themselves lawful, may be to the doers sinful: that which is materially good, may be formally evill, if the person be evil: it's only a good tree that can bring forth good fruit; and a good man, that can do a good work, Mat. 7.17, 18. the best works of wicked men are but <hi>splendida peccata,</hi> glorious sins, and that which is <hi>bonum,</hi> good in it self may not be <hi>bene factum,</hi> well done, nor accepted of God. And so also that which is materially good, may be finally evill, when Gods glory is not made the end as well as Gods will the rule of mens actions: <hi>Jehu</hi> did that which was good, executing Gods Commandement in destroying the posterity of <hi>Ahab</hi> and the Priests of <hi>Baal,</hi> 2 King. 10.11, 25. These actions God approved and rewarded with a temporal blessing, <hi>viz.</hi> that his children did sit upon the throne of Israel, unto the fourth generation, vers. 30. but because <hi>Jehu</hi> did not aim at Gods glory, but his own by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ends and base designs (his word being the glory of God, 2 King. 10.16. but his project being his Masters King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome) therefore we finde God threatning what he had commanded, and punishing what he had rewarded. Hos. 1.4. <hi>I will visit the bloud of</hi> Jezreel <hi>upon the house of</hi> Jehu: But what can be inferred from all this to prove the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>closure of <hi>Catthorp</hi> sinful? rather this very objection from the mouthes of such zealous opposers, doth to me
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:207043:14"/> confirm the equity of our cause and the lawfulnesse of our actions. For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Hereby it's granted, that our Inclosure is not sinful in the matter of it, only they suspect our ends are not right.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Have they reason to suspect that our ends are not right? or we more reason to suspect their censures to be rash? seeing they dare usurp Gods prerogative in search<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our hearts, before they have detected any evil in our actions. Have we discovered that our aims are not at Gods glory, as <hi>Jehu</hi> did? or have not they rather disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered themselves more censorious then becometh Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, by unadvised judgement? Mat. 7.1.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Why is not Gods glory our end? forsooth because we aim at our own gains and advancement of our estates. Are these two ends alwaies incompatible? this a meer <hi>Non sequitur:</hi> may not the bettering of our estates be carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on in subordination to Gods glory? if God inlarge our talents by his blessing upon our lawful endevours, the fault is in our corrupt hearts, and not the Inclosure, if we do not glorifie God so much the more. It is a very strange principle and unheard of paradox, that nothing can be done to Gods glory, which tends to mans profit: Do not tradesmen in following their vocations, aime at their own advantage, do none of them glorifie God thereby? Doth not the husbandman in all his dressing the earth, aime at the harvest? is not gain his end as well as ours? If we do not glorifie God, then all the glory of tillage will be defaced, and the honour of the painfull plowman laid in the dust. But why do I speak of earthly things, do not the Saints in all their doings and sufferings for God, aime both at Gods glory and their own advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, <hi>viz.</hi> the salvation of their souls? Did not <hi>Moses</hi> in all his afflictions with the children of God, aime at his own advantage, Heb. 11.26. He that despised all the glory that <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Court could afford him; he that (<hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raohs</hi> Crown being set upon his head, when he was yet a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:207043:14"/> childe) did take it off and spurn it with his foot, as <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sephus</hi> relateth, He that did willingly choose the sinlesse troubles of oppressed <hi>Israel,</hi> then the sin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ul pleasu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es of triumphing <hi>Egypt:</hi> He by whom God did all those migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty things for his <hi>Israel,</hi> without controversie did glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God: yet had an eye also to the recompence of reward.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>The Inclosure of <hi>Catthorp</hi> laudable.</head>
               <p>IT being proved that the Inclosure of <hi>Catthorp</hi> is Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, I proceed in the next place to prove it Laudable, and that Gods glory is the end as well as Gods will the rule of our actions.</p>
               <p>This will appear in two particulars:
<list>
                     <item>1. It doth procure good.</item>
                     <item>2. It doth prevent evil.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Now if these two be proved, I doubt not but all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous Christians will acknowledge that it doth glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie God, and that it is not to be decryed, as of evill report, but rather truly laudable as well as lawfull.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That it produceth <hi>bonum utile,</hi> a profitable good, I think none will deny; and that this good is also <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num verum &amp; honestum,</hi> consistent with honesty, I thus prove.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Hereby we provide for our families, which is not a sin but a duty, provided alwaies we do it by lawful means, <hi>He that neglecteth this,</hi> the Apostle saith, <hi>is worse then an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidel;</hi> and shall we be accounted Infidels for doing of it? let it be granted, that it is one end to encrease our estates, and make better provision for our families, that both we and ours may be in a better capacity to do God service
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:207043:15"/> and glorifie him the more: all this is our duty; who then can blame us?</p>
               <p n="2">2. It nourisheth wood which is much wanting in their fields or Countreys: wood daily destroyed and cut down; if none be planted, how will after ages be provided?</p>
               <p n="3">3. All the arable ground in the fallow-field, which is of no profit in the common field, will be gained and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit made of it: in Inclosure the land being once soarded, the husbandman needs keep no fallow at all, and yet have more corn upon one acre of new broken up land, then upon three acres in the common field. I lately plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up three acres of old Inclosure in <hi>Cottesbatch,</hi> and gained sixteen quarters of barley, when my Tenant had not so much of two yard land and three quarters in <hi>Catthorp</hi> the same year: the next year I sowed the same Land with wheat and gained thirty five thraves, whereas my Tenant hath seldome had half so much winter-corn upon all my Land in <hi>Catthorp:</hi> so that if he continue but five acres in tillage, plowing sometimes one part of the Land, and at other times another part, he will have more white corn then he had before the Inclosure, and the rest of the arable Land will be gained.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The arable Land in the pease-field may be improved to greater advantage, the pease for the most part being all spent in seed and keeping of horses, and seldome any profit made of them.</p>
               <p n="5">5. In Inclosure men may plow their Land with oxen, which (the harvest being inned) they may feed in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter months and so sell them, and the next year buy others in their room, which will be far more profitable then horse, which in the common fields are for the most part so jaded and tyred with continual labour, that they make little profit of them; or if they deem it more convenient, they may keep good mares whose foales will bring them great profit yearly.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The advancement of private persons will be the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the publick: if Merchants do buy an advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:207043:15"/> commodity,, hath not the Common-wealth an advantage thereby, as well as themselves? if men by good husbandry, trenching, manuring their Land, &amp;c. do bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their Land, is not the Common-wealth inriched there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by? so whatsoever benefit we make to our selves, tends to the publick good.</p>
               <p>Secondly, As Good is procured, so Evil is hereby pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented: two sorts of evils, <hi>malum peccati, &amp; malum poenae,</hi> evil of crime, and evil of pain; evil of sin, and evil of sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row; evil of mens doings and sufferings, mans iniquity and misery are both prevented by a regulated inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure.</p>
               <p>Evils of sin are,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Strife and contention, litigious quarrels and suits of Law, which are daily occasioned by mens trespasses against each other in the open fields, for want of a mound to keep their cattell within their own bounds. Let it se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously be considered, how many brawling contentions are brought before the Judges every Assizes, by the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the common fields; and how few of the like nature by the inhabitants of inclosures, and it will set a seal to this truth.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Falling out of herdsmen, which produceth fighting, battings, and too often murthers.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Many wilful oppressions, men commonly stealing their neighbours corn and grasse that lyeth next them, and turning their cattell loose on purpose, when they pretend they break their tedders: now although wicked men will do this in any place, yet they have not such opportunity to commit such rapines, so secretly without discovery in Inclosures as in common fields; the very occasions of sin are dangerous, take away the occasion and the sin will cease. It's a fair booty that makes many a thief, which possibly would have lived honestly but for the occasion. Opportunity one calleth an woer, which none but hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven can conquer; occasion and a corrupt heart being
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:207043:16"/> like to two inordinate lovers which seldome meet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but they sin together, if we keep them asunder the harm is prevented.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Evils of sorrow, the misery of man and beast hereby prevented.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Common experience teacheth that it preventeth the rotting of sheep, there being usually five rots in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon fields for one in Inclosure, the poor husbandman losing as much in the Rot one year, as he hath gained in seven years before.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The hedges preserve the corn and grasse from spoil by travellers; who know no high waies in the common fields, especially by herds of cattell, which by reason of the extreme narrownesse of the Common, do much harm upon those Lands which butt upon the pasture, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the keepers do their uttermost to prevent it</p>
               <p n="3">3. It prevents that disorderly and irrationall manner of feeding of cattel, and driving them by flocks from place to place, to the great prejudice of the Land and grasse, the cattell staining and spoiling as much with their feet, as they eat with their mouthes; as also the annoyance and disturbance of the cattell by such disorderly driving. Me thinks even pity to the poor beast, should invite men to sever their pasture from their arable land, that so they may feed and drink when they desire it without disturbance. But many are so wilful that they will not change any of their old customes, although they can give no more reason for it, then the savage <hi>Irish</hi> for their drawing their plowes by the horse tails without har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It preventeth that insufferable wrong both to man and beast, in keeping more cattell then the fields can bear, which impoverisheth man, and pineth the beast: True, it's granted fewer cattell are kept in improved grounds, but one cow or sheep will yeeld as much profit as three in the common fields.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:207043:16"/>5. It preventeth the intolerable toyle and unnecessary charge of the husbandman;</p>
               <p n="1">1. In tilling his Land; it requiring three or four tilths in the common field, without which it will bear no corn, whereas in Inclosure farre lesse Land will yeeld more corn with one tilth. In the common fields the ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Land turns the husbandman to little profit, his great pains and cost considered, which I conceive is the reason of that maxime of the husbandman, That he that gives more Rent for his Land then the Hay and Commons are worth, hath but a hard bargain: his labour and charge in dressing seeds and inning, amounting to near as much as his Crop of grain is worth.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In gathering his Corn and Hay together, speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Hay, which lyeth in so many little parcels, in bulks and hades, and at such a distance, that it costs near as much in gathering as it is worth.</p>
               <p n="6">6. It preventeth the oppression of the poor husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, which is not able to store his own Commons, which the rich man devoureth with his cattell, and so puts the poor mans profit into his own purse.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>It is not Laudable although Lawful, because three Ministers having a hand in it, others will be incouraged to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>close other Towns unlawfully.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> If any plead our example, I hope they will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so follow it in all circumstances wherewith it is clothed, and then their inclosures will be lawfull as well as ours; if otherwise, they have no reason to plead our example, but rather our good example will condemn their sinful Inclosure.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>It is at least the appearance of evil, and Christians, much more Ministers must avoid not only evil, but the appearance of it,</hi> 2 Thess. 5.22.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ</hi> 1. That the appearance of evil is prohibited, is l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st Christians should fall into evil, which they think good, through mistake; some sins are palpable, which we may feel; some visible, which we may see; others
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:207043:17"/> of a finer thread, it's difficult to discern them; some sins are open, and others are much disguised: upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count Gods people ought to watch, l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st they rush upon these disguised sins, but let our Inclosure be unbowelled and unmasked, and no evil appeareth in it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> 2. I grant it a duty not only to provide for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science by shunning evil, but for same by avoiding the appearance of it; the jewel of a good name must be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for, Phil. 4.8. the credit of the Gospel depends upon those that professe it, much more those that preach it: because through their sides the Gospels glory is much wounded, therefore Christians must avoid not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note n="*" place="margin">Bernard.</note>
                  <hi>Malas res sed malas pariter species,</hi> not only evil things but the shewes of evil. Such things as are evil in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, and such things as are bruited to be evil in their circumstances. Thus <hi>Paul</hi> did abstain from things lawful, rather then offend weak brethren, 1 Cor. 8.13. He would not eat meat while the world stood, rather then offend; so in the first plantation of the Gospel he choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth manual labour, and requireth not Gospel mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, to avoid the suspicion of being mercenary: but here note, that in avoiding the appearance of evil, three things are considerable.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Whether the persons offended be weak or wilful; what <hi>Paul</hi> did, was in compliance with weak Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, young neophytes, which were not yet informed that those that preach the Gospel ought to live of the Gospel: should <hi>Pauls</hi> practise be pressed upon the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters of the Gospel now, would not all Christians an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer that this was in the Churches infancy, when weak Christians did not know their du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y; but now under the glorious shining of the Gospel of peace, this truth is clearly made known in the word, to every Christian that is not wilful: if therefore Ministers should now give up their Right, this was not to satisfie the weak, but to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the wilful: so it being clearly detected and demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strated, that our Inclosure of <hi>Catthorp</hi> is a thing lawful
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:207043:17"/> and good must needs professe. I conceive them not weak Christians, but wilful travellers, that call it the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of evil.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whether the thing done be a Real appearance of Evil, or only Imaginary.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Real, when the fact it self or circumstances do give ground of suspicion. Or,</p>
               <p n="2">2. Imaginary, which is framed and fancied out of prejudice without any colour of reason. That our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour did heal on the Sabbath day was to the Pharisees an appearance of evil, but fancied by their ignorance ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then afforded by the fact, it being a work of chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and one part of the duty of the day whereby it is san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whether the thing in question be a thing indifferent, or absolutely good and a part of duty: It's a ruled case, That no duty ought to be neglected because it is suspected to be evil; although evil may not be done that good may come, yet good must be done although it seem evil. We must avoid the appearance of evil, but it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes not that we must avoid evident and transparent good, which our Inclosure is fully proved to be.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>The people are generally offended at it, and cry out against all inclosure as oppression, therefore it is at least a thing of evil report, and to be avoided.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> All things are not of an evill report in the Scripture sense, which the multitude decry as evil: the best things now a daies are worst spoken of by the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, the very name of Reformation is as much explo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the vulgar as Inclosure; those sacred ordinances of Magistracy and Ministery, which God hath honoured with his own approbation and stamped with his own superscription, Rom. 13.1. Heb. 13.17. are now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come offensive to the levelling multitude: Suppose that some under the specious pretence of reformation, would bring in deformation; is therefore all reall reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on according to Gods Word to be rejected? Suppose
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:207043:18"/> some Magistrates and Ministers have miscarried and done amisse, must therefore these Ordinances of God be laid aside? God forbid; these miscarriages were <hi>vitia persona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum non rei,</hi> the faults of the men, not the office: Let it be granted that some Inclosers have destroyed Towns and oppressed the poor, and thereby have raised an evil report upon Inclosures in general, must we therefore lay aside all our hopes of reformation of the common field confusion by bringing them into the discipline of a regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated Inclosure? A hedge in the field is as necessary in its kinde, as government in the Church or Common-wealth. When God threatens to lay waste his vineyard, the Church and Common-wealth of Israel, it's said, <hi>I will take away the hedge thereof,</hi> Isa. 5.6. <hi>viz.</hi> Magistracy and Ministry, those props and pillars of the Church and State, which are here compared to a hedge inclosing the vineyard or field; as also Gods Church is called a <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den inclosed,</hi> Cant. 4.12. Had God been such an enemy to hedges as some pretend, the Holy Ghost would not have made use of this metaphor, to signifie those his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Ordinances: if God in judgement removed the hedges of Israel, I hope it will be a mercy and not a judgement, to enjoy the benefit of hedges in <hi>Catthorp,</hi> whatsoever the multitude say to the contrary? This is our comfort, God must judge us, not the multitude; if we have the approbation of God, we care not much for the applause of men: our betters before us did passe through an ill report as well as good, 2 Cor. 6.8. It is a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond confort, that those reall commodities and conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences, which we and ours hope to enjoy by this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>closure, will do us more good than all the vanity of popular applause: that maxime, <hi>vox populi, vox Dei,</hi> to be understood, <hi>vox populi Dei,</hi> the voice of the people, the voyce of God (that is) the voice of Gods people, is the voice of God, not <hi>aura popularis,</hi> that airy blast of the vulgar breath, which turns with every winde, and is for the most part as unconstant as it is groundlesse.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:207043:18"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> 2. I desire in all things so to demean my self, as to give no just offence to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Jew nor Gentile, nor to the Church of Christ, to those that are within, nor to those that are without; but there are scandals taken which are not given; if any take offence without cause, the scandall will lie at their own homes and not at ours. I meet with four sorts of men offended at Inclosure, whom I intreat not to be angry if by vindication of our selves, I set the saddle on the right horse, and lay the bastard of scandall at the door of the right owners.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The first and most that are offended at Inclosure, are the ruder sort of people; which to speak truly, have most reason: Why? <hi>Vivitur ex rapto:</hi> they live upon rapine and spoil of others, and seldome keep their cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell within their own bounds, but daily make a prey upon their neighbours corn and grasse: stoln waters are sweet to these pretended upright men, whose consciences cannot bear the burthen of Inclosure, yet make no conscience when they can do it without discovery to overstore their Commons, and plow up their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours Land, &amp;c. There is a profane and levelling spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit now abroad in the world that cry out against go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and speak evil of dignities; What would they have! forsooth liberty of conscience: form what? from Magistracy and Ministry; to what? to live as the list and sin <hi>cum privilegio;</hi> the golden reins of discipline please not, this yoke they cannot bear, but cast off this, and then they may swear, and lie, and rob, and rifle, and swill, and swagger, riot and revell in a shorelesse excesse, and set sin on horseback to ride in triumph without controll whither it listeth. True, liberty of consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence a precious Jewell, but this a liberty from sin, not a liberty to sin. The very same spirit of disorder in the very same persons, and upon the same grounds doth decry Inclosure, because it would put a bridle upon
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:207043:19"/> their licencious lusts: if such as these are offended at our Inclosure, is it a thing of evill report in us to prevent their disorders, and enormous sins?</p>
               <p n="2">2. A second sort of men that are offended at our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>closure, are some self-ended Graziers, which have much in their mouthes that woe pronounced by the Prophet <hi>Isaiah</hi> against such as lay land to land; which I must needs retort upon themselves, because they make no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of taking Lands over poor mens heads, and are never contented till they have got into their hands as much Land as would maintain ten Families, yet they exclaim against Inclosure, why? Because a general In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>closure and division between the arable and pasture Land, would spoyle their trad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, in that husbandmen would keep as good Cattel as themselves, so that they could not Monopolize all the fat Beef and Mutton to themselves, as now they do: I hope it is not of evill report to crosse the avarice and frustrate the expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of such self-ended and self-condemned persons, who live upon Inclosure themselves, and yet would have none inclose but themselves.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A fourth sort offended are some truly godly, and you will say, Dare you offend them?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> For my own part, I had rather not only that <hi>Catthorp</hi> should never be Inclosed, but that my Land there had never been enjoyed by me, then that I should justly offend the least of Gods little ones, but I am very sorry that these should take offence where none is given: what should I do in this case? the godly are divided in judgement about this point, some for it, others against it, I must necessarily offend one party. Which should I choose?</p>
               <p n="1">1. Those that are for it, might justly have challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged me, if I had denied my consent to that which (my conscience bearing me witnesse that I lye not) I am ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perswaded is not only lawfull but necessary at leas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:207043:19"/>
                  <hi>ad bene esse,</hi> to the well being of the Common-wealth; hereby I should have hindred others, and such as I hope are godly, from the lawfull improvement of their own estate, of which I could render no reason, but that I would not offend those godly, which are of a different perswasion from them and my self also; would not my refusal, <hi>rebus sic stantibus,</hi> have given more just cause of offence to them, then my consent hath given to others? Let moderate men judge.</p>
               <p n="2">2. What is it that offendeth the brethren of another judgement?</p>
               <p n="1">1. Is it our exchange of lands with each other? that hath been done many times in common fields, and no such offence taken at it by the persons now of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Is it a making a hedge about our Lands? this also ordinary in the common fields: if it be lawfull to make a hedge between the bounds of Town and Town, why not also between the limits of neighbour and neighbour?</p>
               <p n="3">3. I suppose they take offence, because they fear de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>population, oppression, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> They fear, but prove it not, I have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy proved the contrary: whether their groundlesse fear and unjust clamours, or our regular actions are most justly offensive, let moderate men judge between us and them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Are not many places in <hi>England, Essex, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, Devonshire, Shropshire, Worcester,</hi> wholly inclosed, and yet no such effects follow? Are any of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in those parts offended at it? why then are any offended at <hi>Leicestershire?</hi> is the same action lawful in one place, and yet sinful in another? by what law? sure I am, those that write most vehemently against Inclosure, have granted these Inclosures lawfull, as Mr. <hi>Hallhead</hi> in his Book entituled, <hi>Inclosure thrown open,</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:207043:20"/> in answering this objection concerning other parts of <hi>England,</hi> hath these words. I would not be mistaken, I mean only depopulating Inclosure, &amp;c. Yea the most strenuous opposers of Inclosure in generall, and our Inclosure in particular, have acknowledged, that if all places were inclosed, no such effects would follow: if it be lawfull to inclose all, then by an argument, <hi>a majore ad minus,</hi> from the greater to the lesse, it's lawfull to inclose some: Would they not be offended, if all <hi>Leicestershire</hi> and the Counties adjacent were Inclosed: why then are they offended at the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>closure of our small village of <hi>Catthorp?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. I am informed by such as have travelled in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to other Nations, that there is no Land that lyeth in that confused manner, by small parcels, roods and half acres, as it doth in our parts of <hi>England,</hi> even in <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> every man hath his Land lying together: are these parts of <hi>England</hi> wiser then all the Christian world besides? are they all in the dark? doe they live in daily sin? or rather doe not we need a reformation by a regulated Inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure?</p>
               <p n="6">6. The Lands of the Israelites and other Lands mentioned in holy Writ, were not divided into small parcels as are our common fields, Gen. 23.9. The field which <hi>Abraham</hi> bought of <hi>Ephron</hi> the <hi>Hittite,</hi> did belong to <hi>Ephron</hi> alone, we read of no fellow Commoners that joyned in the sale of it: It cost <hi>Abraham</hi> four hundred shekels of silver, vers. 16. how much a shekel was the learned agree not: <hi>Junius</hi> saith the Hebrew Shekels was two shilling, four pence, others five groats: the difference may arise from the difference between the common shekel, and the Shekel of the Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: the common shekel some say was but half so much: the most probable opinion is, that a Shekel did weigh half an ounce of silver, which in our money
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:207043:20"/> is two shillings six pence;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Willet</hi> on Exod. 30.13.</note> Doctor <hi>Willet</hi> is of this perswasion; his ground he hath from <hi>Arias Monta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> who relates that one Rabbi <hi>Moses</hi> travelling from <hi>Spain</hi> to <hi>Palestina,</hi> saw a piece of silver with this inscription, <hi>SHEKEL ISRAEL,</hi> and the pot of Manna on the one side, and holy <hi>Jerusalem</hi> with the Rod of <hi>Aaron</hi> blossoming on the other side, in the ancient Samaritan character, (which without doubt was the true Hebrew character, that now used being the Chaldee, which the <hi>Israelites</hi> first used after their return from <hi>Babylon,</hi> to distinguish themselves from <hi>Samaritans</hi>). This the said Rabbi weighed, and it came to half an ounce: he saw also a lesser piece with the same Characters, supposed to be the half shekel mentioned in Scripture: <hi>Beza</hi> also had a piece of the same coyne, which was given him by his friend <hi>Ambrosius Blanzerus,</hi> the expresse image where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, he doth graphically delineate, <hi>Major. Annot.</hi> Mat. 17.24. Now four hundred shekels at this rate, would amount to fifty pound of our English money; or if the common shekel was but half so much, yet it was a very large summe in <hi>Abrahams</hi> daies, and therefore pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable it was a very large field: yea this field was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>closed too, vers. 17. He bought also the trees in the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders rouud about.</p>
               <p>And so also it was in <hi>Egypt,</hi> every man had his field peculiar, Gen. 47.20. in the time of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, every man sold his field to <hi>Pharaoh</hi> for bread, the Land then lay not in little parcels but in large fields.</p>
               <p>When the <hi>Israelites</hi> were setled in the promised Land, every man had his own field, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.5. if any mans beast did hurt anothers field, he was to make restituti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n out of the best of his own field. So the <hi>Israelites</hi> were prohibit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d to covet their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours field, Deut. 5.21. Again it was a custome for
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:207043:21"/> some in <hi>Israel</hi> to dedicate their fields to God for pious uses, Levit. 17.18, 19. Surely they did not dedicate that which was not their own. <hi>Achsah Oth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niels</hi> wife, <hi>Calebs</hi> daughter, did beg of her Father a field, Joshua 15.18. which shee would not have done, if it had not been <hi>Calebs</hi> own to give: he had no fellow commoners to obstruct his bounty. <hi>Ruth</hi> gleaned in the field of <hi>Boaz,</hi> Ruth 2.3. Her hap was to light on a part of the field belonging to <hi>Boaz,</hi> not as some affirm, that <hi>Boaz</hi> had only a part of the field, or that part only on which she gleaned, but that she gleaned on a part of that field which did wholly belong to <hi>Boaz:</hi> no interpreters or translators, judge that part of the field only to belong to <hi>Boaz. Junius</hi> and <hi>Trem.</hi> render it, <hi>accidit ea casu possessio agri pertinentis ad Boazum.</hi> The possession of the field be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to <hi>Boaz,</hi> hapned to her by chance, the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar translation attributed to <hi>Hierome: accidit ut ille a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger dominum habebat nomine Boaz.</hi> It hapned that that field had one called <hi>Boaz</hi> for its owner: I confesse this is rather an Interpretation then a translation, the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew verbatim being translated, <hi>Et accidit casus ejus por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio agri ad Boazum:</hi> Her chance hapned to be part of the field belonging to <hi>Boaz:</hi> but all agree, and none de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that the whole field was his, hence vers. 22. <hi>Naom</hi> chargeth <hi>Ruth</hi> that the maidens of <hi>Boaz</hi> see her not in any other field, not any other part of the field. The same <hi>Boaz</hi> when he marryed <hi>Ruth,</hi> bought the field of <hi>Naomi,</hi> Ruth 4.5. When the Philistines sent back the Ark of the Lord, the cart was brought into the field of <hi>Josua</hi> the <hi>Bethshemite;</hi> the other inhabitants of <hi>Beth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>shemesh</hi> had its like other fields, but this field belonge to <hi>Joshua</hi> only, 1 Sam. 6.14, 18. Again, <hi>Absalon</hi> cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed his servants to set on fire <hi>Joabs</hi> field of corn, 2 Sam. 14.30, 31. And <hi>Jeremiah</hi> bought the field of <hi>Hanameel</hi> his uncles son, Jer. 32.9. By all which it plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears
<pb facs="tcp:207043:21"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:207043:22"/>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:207043:22"/> that these fields lay not in common; but every particular field had its peculiar propriator or owner. When the Scripture mentioneth Land belonging to Towns, it speaks in the plural number, as <hi>Lachish</hi> and the fields thereof, Neh. 11.30. but when any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar mans field, in the singular, <hi>Josuas</hi> field, <hi>Joabs</hi> field, &amp;c. And it's probable that some of these fields were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>closed, hence the Kings workmen are said to dwell among plants and hedges, 1 Chron. 4.23. Now if this be so, do we give just offence to our brethren by lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Land after the platform of the Lands of Gods own people, which were so divided by Gods own ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment? or do not rather our brethren take offence when none on our part is given?</p>
               <p>Lastly, I have heard that our Lands in <hi>England</hi> were never divided into such small parcels till the daies of K. <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror, who fearing the people did disaffect him, out of State policy commanded the Lands to be so divided, that the people being busied about division of their Lands, might have no leisure to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturb his Government: if this be so, it's no just offence to restore our Lands to their pristine order.</p>
               <p>Thus having I hope fully proved what I at first pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised, <hi>viz.</hi> that our Inclosure of <hi>Catthorp</hi> is both law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and laudable, I conclude with this serious professi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that if any in the spirit of love and meeknesse, by soft words and sound reasons, shall evince our Inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure to be sinful, I shall as publickly acknowledge it as I have openly defended our action. Obstinacy in any thing I judge Idolatry, the covetous man makes his mammon' his god, and the haeretick his opinion, in that <hi>Narcissus</hi> like he is in love with his own shadow, and the chimaera of his own brain: for my part it's my desire, <hi>herbam dare veritati,</hi> (when ever error appeareth to be an error) to sit down conquered, and give truth
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:207043:23"/> the victory: this I best relish in others, and by Gods grace will endevour to practise my self. It can be no disgrace to be overcome by truth, it's no part of levity nor inconstancy, to change falshood for truth, and upon fight of error to change both opinion and practise: and with holy <hi>Augustine</hi> ingenuously retract what hath been said or done amisse, so God shall have the glory, and our souls the comfort.</p>
               <p>But on the other hand, if any shall persevere in their groundlesse reproaches of us: <hi>magna &amp; susquipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalia verba sus{que} de{que} habeo.</hi> Lofty long footed words, or to use the Apostles expression, Jude 16. Great swelling words of vanity, which have no more weight than a feather, I care not much for. These may hurt themselves but cannot hurt me, who am resolved to answer all such opprobrious language, as once <hi>Tacitus</hi> did answer railing <hi>Metullus. Tu didicisti male dicere, Ego didici male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicta contemnere:</hi> thou hast learned to revile, I have lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to slight thy revilings.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:207043:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>